<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Flatiron School | My Octopress Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://heatherlim.github.io/blog/categories/flatiron-school/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://heatherlim.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-25T21:45:53-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://heatherlim.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Your Name]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Things Coming Round Again and the Importance of Thinking Before Coding]]></title>
    <link href="http://heatherlim.github.io/blog/2015/10/25/my-first-post-on-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-25T20:44:04-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://heatherlim.github.io/blog/2015/10/25/my-first-post-on-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m still working on my cute random group sample code because spending hours solving a &ldquo;problem&rdquo; that probably takes up just ten minutes of your time doing manually is a fun thing to do. It really is.</p>

<p>Anyway, it has made a lot of progress from before. I remembered that I was so uncomfortable with classes two weeks ago&hellip; and now&hellip; well I&rsquo;m still not as comfortable as I&rsquo;d like to be but I&rsquo;m actually using them now which is a plus. Something I learned while working on this is that sometimes the best way to solve a problem is the simplest approach. I was so excited about using .sample that I ignored some of the more obvious methods to use. Instead, I used .sample and .pop to pull random people from the array.</p>

<p>This is a section of my original code:
<code>
def random_group(people, groupnumber)
  random_person = people.sample
  binding.pry
  group_array = []
   Array.new(groupnumber) {people.sample }
    people.each do |each_person|
      if each_person != random_person
        group_array &lt;&lt; random_person
        people.delete_if {|repeat_person| repeat_person == random_person}
        binding.pry
      elsif each_person == random_person
        people.delete_if {|repeat_person| repeat_person == random_person}
      end     
    end
</code>
If you can&rsquo;t decipher what the hell is going on, that&rsquo;s fine because it didn&rsquo;t work and I could barely tell myself what I was doing. First warning sign I suppose that I should find a different approach.</p>

<p>My problem I outlined in my previous post was that .sample would take a random person out of the array but there when the method was run again, there was still a chance to pick the same person out of the array. The person wasn&rsquo;t actually removed in the array. While I had thought I could use .pop, that method would not be random.</p>

<p>The solution was to use .shuffle before .pop was used. This way, I can now pick random people out of the array until it was empty. I wasted a lot of time with .sample because I was too focused in using .sample than using the right tool for the job. I&rsquo;m not saying using .sample is impossible but .shuffle and .pop made mroe sense to me.</p>

<p>Now my code has two methods that make the hash and fill it.</p>

<pre><code>def create_groups 
     range = (1..@groupnumber).to_a
     range.each do |indgroup| # 1, 2, 3, 4...
     @groups["group" + " " + "#{indgroup}"] = []
    end  
    @groups
  end

  def filling_group
    people_number = @people.count/@groupnumber
    range = (1..@groupnumber).to_a
     range.each do |indgroup|
        @groups["group" + " " + "#{indgroup}"] &lt;&lt; @people.shuffle!.pop(people_number)    
          @groups.values.each do |x|
            x.flatten!
         end
     end 
  end
</code></pre>

<p>With this, I had fulfilled the first goal I set. Right now, my code could create x number of groups for x amount of people. I added the code below as well so that it would be possible for people to be divided into groups even if the groups were uneven. Like 20 people could be divided into 7 groups and so on.</p>

<pre><code>def if_uneven
    range = (1..@people.count).to_a
    range.each do |indgroup|
      @groups["group" + " " + "#{indgroup}"] &lt;&lt; @people.shuffle!.pop
    end
  end
</code></pre>

<p>After people are sorted into groups, the remaining number of people would in the people array would be iterated through again and distributed amoungst the groups already made.</p>

<p>And now comes the part where thinking ahead would have really helped me out. I had thought that being able to sort people randomly into groups was the first step in my project. The second step would be to show all other unique possibilities of groups. Though I could keep running the program, it does not actually &ldquo;remember&rdquo; the last distribution it made. So it is highly possible that if Person 1 and Person 2 were paired together, they could be paired together again whether in the same group or a different one.</p>

<p>I spent awhile thinking about how to make the program remember what groups each person was put into and make sure they&rsquo;d never be in a group where some of their original group mates were. Should I use databases to store this information? Or I could make an even bigger hash. I could place
<code>
groups = {
  :group1 =&gt; [],
  :group2 =&gt; [],
  :group3 =&gt; [],
  :group4 =&gt; [],
  :group5 =&gt; []
}
</code>
into a hash with values of days. So it would be Day 1 => groups&hellip; Day 2 => groups&hellip;</p>

<p>But then I realized that my problem was a symptom of not thinking ahead. If I were going to list out all possible unique combinations, why the hell was I randomizing it? Instead, I needed a method that would pick out the groups in the exact same way each time.</p>

<p>So thinking ahead would have saved me a lot of time though in the end I still learned a lot. Though just for more practice I decided to try make my program into a webapp to get more familiar with sinatra. The final result is a page that would show groups and their random distribution whenever it gets refreshed. Eventually I&rsquo;d like to make a form where people can simply input the number of groups they want and the people they want to sort.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I Had Problems With Arrays/Hashes/Pigeons... (and What Else I Learned)]]></title>
    <link href="http://heatherlim.github.io/blog/2015/10/06/first-blog-post/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-06T21:04:50-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://heatherlim.github.io/blog/2015/10/06/first-blog-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<center>
<img src ="http://heatherlim.github.io/images/pigeon_photo.jpg" width ="300">
</center>


<p>Iteration was my first challenge that I didn&rsquo;t really know what to make of. I went through great pains to not use it. On the first lab where we had to write a method that could tel if a number was prime or not, instead of iterating through the whole array range to see if there were more than two zeroes (the array represented the number being divided by 1 to that particular number. So the first element in the array would be that number divided by one, the second element would be that number divided by two and so on&hellip; if the number was prime, the modulo should return only two 0s), I would instead sort the array and check if array[2] == 0.</p>

<p>So already by avoiding it, I made it harder for myself to pick up. It was probably the first method that didn&rsquo;t look to be in plain English for me. It was pretty abstract.</p>

<pre><code>basket = ["apple 1","apple 2","apple 3","apple 4","apple 5","apple 6","apple 7","apple 8","apple 9","apple 10"]

basket.each do |apple|
    puts "Taking out #{apple}"
end
</code></pre>

<p>It didn&rsquo;t click until later that the word between the | | could be anything. In this case it is apple because it describes each element of the array that is picked up. But it is only for ease of understanding. It could be |oranges| for all the program cares.</p>

<p>It also helped me to visualize what&rsquo;s going on. Basically it was as though a pedantic person was going over each item in the array one by one and then executing whatever the instructions below told him to. So apple (or whatever is between the ||) would be equal to the string &ldquo;apple 1&rdquo; and then &ldquo;apple 2&rdquo; and so on&hellip;</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a step by step process that I guess I could read as for each item in the array, do this to that item. And that started to make it clearer for me rather than what I thinking before. That it was some kind of magic thing that did something all at once. Figuring out the plain English equivalent made it also easier for me to finish the pigeon hash lab where we had to sort out pigeons by their names and attributes. The tricky part was understanding what exactly you were getting between those ||.</p>

<center>
<img src ="http://heatherlim.github.io/images/pigeon_box.jpg" width ="300">
</center>


<p>Because I found iteration difficult, on my own time, I decided to make a cute program that would be able to take in a bunch of people and divide them into however many groups the user would want. The program would return different groups each time it was run.</p>

<p>For example, while the input would look something like this:</p>

<pre><code>people = ["Adrian", "Polly", "John", "Ivan", "Jack", "Tom", "Anna", "Mary", "Ben", "Jeff",
"Alex", "Megan", "Helen", "Sarah", "Wei", "Aristo", "Jane", "Meredith", "Liz", "Lacey"]
</code></pre>

<p>The output will be in this format:
```
groups = {
   :group1 => [-names here-],
   :group2 => [-names here-],
   :group3 => [-names here-],
   :group4 => [-names here-],
   :group5 => [-names here-]
    }</p>

<pre><code>Because I wanted to find a random person from the people array, I thought why not find a random number with rand() and make the number inside rand to be people.count? Then, if I named that variable something, I could call it into people[random] and it should return a random person from the array.
</code></pre>

<p>random = rand(people.count)
  people[random]</p>

<pre><code>After this, I would be able to shovel in random people into their arrays as long as the people inside each of their arrays would not exceed the people.length/groupnumber. Which makes sense because if the array has 20 people in it, and we want to make five groups, each group would have four people in it.

However, even though I made progress with feeling more comfortable with iteration, I found it difficult to return a different random person each time so my groups would always be filled with the same random person. My logic was something like how can I iterate over my random variable if it wasn't an array? Then I tried some stuff with iterating over the people array and only shoveling in each person if the person value was equal to the random person value...

In any case, it didn't quite work out and I found a different method to get four different people into the array. So first I wanted to make an array with variables in it equal to the number of people I wanted in the group. So let that variable be called people_in_group (which would be the length of the people array divided by the number of groups we want).
</code></pre>

<p>Array.new(people_in_group)</p>

<pre><code>Now this should create an array with a bunch of nils. But we can use .sample

.sample can choose a random element from the array
</code></pre>

<p>Array.new(people_in_group){people.sample}</p>

<p>```
This will fill the new array with random people until the number of elements it has is equal to the number of people we want in the group.</p>

<p>Right now I&rsquo;m working on making sure there are no repeated people inside each array. Then I will make sure the people do not repeat in each group.</p>

<p>So hopefully completing this mini program will help me out further with iteration and sorting. In any case, maybe I&rsquo;ll be qualified enough as an entry-level pigeon sorter.</p>

<p>My current trouble is now with classes. So hopefully by the next time I make another post I&rsquo;ll be confident enough to write a little about it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
